<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Touch The Invisible</title>
    <description>A University of Pittsburgh Research Project. Bridging Physical and Digital Modeling of Biological Macromolecules
</description>
    <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://touchtheinvisible.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 20:20:14 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2024 20:20:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>La-related Protein 1 (LARP1)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;La-related protein 1 (LARP1) is a conserved RNA-binding protein that plays a key role in post-transcriptional regulation of gene expression. LARP1 specifically binds to TOP mRNA targets to regulate their stability and translation. Canonically LARP1 has a repressive role in translation of TOP mRNA, but they have been found to be upregulated in some cancers suggesting an unknown activation role. Because of their prevalence in cancers, LARP1 is a novel target for many studies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 14:31:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/04/03/larp1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/04/03/larp1/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Insulin</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Insulin is a peptide hormone secreted by the beta cells of pancreas. As a signaling molecule, it prompts cells to uptake glucose, effectively decreasing glucose levels in the blood. Cells respond to this signal by incorporating glucose transporters (GLUTs) into their membranes. Glucose diffuses through GLUTs into the cells and is immediately metabolized or stored for later use in the form of glycogen in liver and muscle tissue. Initially, insulin is made of 110 amino acids, but after cellular processing, the mature monomer consists of 51 amino acids, making it one of the smallest proteins in the human body. Insulin is stored in hexamer structures coordinated by central zinc ions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:21:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/26/insulin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/26/insulin/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Zinc Finger Protein Motif</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Zinc finger is a structural motif found in many different nucleic acid binding proteins. It contains one or more zinc ions that stabilize the way the protein folds around DNA. Zinc finger binds to DNA and acts as a transcription factor, regulating synthesis of RNA from a DNA template. It is also found in proteins involved in DNA repair, RNA binding, protein degradation, and signal transduction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:15:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/26/zinc-finger-protein-motif/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/26/zinc-finger-protein-motif/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Catabolite Activator Protein</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Catabolite Activator Protein (also known as cAMP receptor protein, CRP) activates transcription of more than a hundred promoters, allowing for synthesis of various enzymes required for degradation of non-glucose molecules. Structurally, it forms a homodimer with a DNA binding site, a cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP), and an RNA polymerase. The cAMP acts as an allosteric regulator to activate CAP, promoting expression of metabolic genes. For example, in bacteria (such as &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt;), the CAP activation is essential for Lac operon expression, allowing for production of β-galactosidase, an enzyme that breaks down milk sugar (lactose to make it available for cellular energy metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2022 19:03:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/26/catabolite-activator-protein/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/26/catabolite-activator-protein/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aminoacyl tRNA Synthetase</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases are enzymes that link amino acids to their cognate tRNAs, forming aminoacyl-tRNAs (a process called “aa-charging”). Using the energy from ATP hydrolysis, an AARS catalyzes covalent bond formation between the tRNA and its amino acid. These charged aminoacyl-tRNAs bring amino acids to ribosomes for protein production. AARSs are ubiquitously expressed by all forms of life. In addition to biosynthesis, AARSs are also involved in regulation of gene expression, intron splicing, development, and activation of immune system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2022 03:03:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/25/aminoacyl-trna-synthetase/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/25/aminoacyl-trna-synthetase/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Phosphofructokinase</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Phosphofructokinase is a key enzymes regulating glycolysis, a carbohydrate metabolism energy pathway. It catalyzes the 3rd step of glycolysis when it transfers a phosphoryl group from ATP to a fructose-6-phosphate, producing fructose 1,6-bisphosphate. It is allosterically inhibited by the product of the metabolic pathway (mechanism known as feedback inhibition): when cellular levels of ATP are high, ATP binds to the allosteric site and inhibits PFK, stopping glycolysis and ATP production. PFK is found in the cytoplasm of bacterial, plant, fungal, and animal cells. Humans produce  several isoforms of PFK, depending on the energetic needs of particular cellular tissue.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2022 02:46:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/25/phosphofructokinase/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/25/phosphofructokinase/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aquaporin</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Aquaporins are integral membrane proteins that are expressed in almost every organism. They form transmembrane channels allowing for fast diffusion of water molecules across cellular membranes. Some aquaporins also transport small solutes such as K+, Na+, NH3, or glycerol. An aquaporin structure is composed of a bundle of 6 alpha helices. These monomers combine into homotetramers or heteroteramers, but each monomer serves as a channel for water molecules. Aquaporins are essential for the water transport system in plants and the tolerance to drought and salt stresses. In human kidneys, delivery of aquaporins into cellular membranes is regulated by the antidiuretic hormone, allowing water reabsorption when dehydrated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 01:31:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/24/aquaporin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/24/aquaporin/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gramicidin</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Gramicidin is a naturally occurring antibiotic protein secreted by the bacterium &lt;em&gt;Bacillus brevis&lt;/em&gt;. Structurally, it is composed of two identical monomeric helices forming a transmembrane channel. The channel portion of the protein facilitates the diffusion of ions across the membrane, disrupting the natural ion distribution across the cellular membrane, eventually leading to cell death. In the natural environment, &lt;em&gt;B. brevis&lt;/em&gt; secretes the protein to outcompete other bacteria and fungi in the environment. Gramicidin has been used in treatment of topical infections for the antibiotic effect on a diverse range of bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 14:31:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/22/gramicidin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/22/gramicidin/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DNA</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;DNA is a hereditary molecule that stores genetic information for all organisms and some viruses. It also serves as a blueprint for the cellular production of proteins and regulatory molecules. DNA is a nucleic acid polymer build from 4 different nucleotides – adenine (A), cytosine (C), guanine (G), and thymine (T). Structurally, it folds into a double helix with a sugar phosphate backbone on the outside and nitrogenous bases on the inside. Complementary bases (A-T, C-G) form hydrogen bonds within the core of the double helix. DNA is found in the nucleus of eukaryotes, in the nucleoids of bacteria, and in the capsids of DNA viruses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 14:31:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/22/dna/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/22/dna/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hexokinase</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hexokinase is an enzyme involved in energy metabolism as it phosphorylates hexose in the rate-limiting step of glycolysis. Once it catalyzes the transfer of the phosphate group, the new product glucose-6-phosphate must be used in an energy metabolic pathway including glycolysis, storage, or pentose phosphate pathway. Hexokinase is allosterically inhibited by its product if there are high levels of glucose-6-phosphate present in the cell. It is found in bacterial, fungal, plant, and animal cells especially in the tissues with high energy demands, such as heart, skeletal, and adipose tissues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 14:31:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/22/hexokinase-copy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://touchtheinvisible.com/2022/03/22/hexokinase-copy/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
